<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Argument against a standing army rectified, and the reflections and remarks upon it in several pamphlets, consider'd in a letter to a friend.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25778</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3632</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12685776</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12685776</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65765</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25778)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65765)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 972:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Argument against a standing army rectified, and the reflections and remarks upon it in several pamphlets, consider'd in a letter to a friend.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-30 [i.e. 28], p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65765:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65765:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Argument AGAINST <hi>A Standing Army.</hi> RECTIFY'D.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65765:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65765:2"/>
            <p>THE ARGUMENT AGAINST A Standing Army Rectified, AND THE Reflections and Remarks upon it IN <hi>Several Pamphlets, Conſider'd.</hi> In a Letter to a Friend. The Lords and Commons Aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter, January,</hi> 22. 1688. in order to ſuch an Eſtabliſhment, as that our Religion, Laws and Liberties might not again be in Danger of being ſubverted, declar'd, <hi>That the Raiſing or Keeping a Standing Army within the Kingdom in time of Peace, unleſs it be by Conſent of Parliament, is againſt Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Pro Rege, &amp; Patria.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:65765:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65765:3"/>
            <head>THE ARGUMENT AGAINST A Standing Army, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Anſwer to your Deſire, to ſend you my own Thoughts, and thoſe of our Friends here concerning the <hi>Arguments</hi> Pro and Con about a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> I have ſent you them as follows, but muſt tell you that we are not Opinionative, and ſhall be glad, as al good Subjects ought to be, to acquieſce in whatever the Wiſdom of the Nation, now Aſſembled in <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſhall think fit to determine in theſe Matters.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:65765:4"/>
            <p>The Author of the <hi>Argument</hi> hath in my Opinion diſcovered a great deal of Reaſon and Wit, and no leſs Affection to his Prince and Country, however he may be traduc'd by ſome who are very much inferiour to him in alll thoſe good Qualifications.</p>
            <p>Yet I muſt beg his Leave to think that his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable Zeal for the Welfare and Security of his Country, hath carry'd him a little too far. So that inſtead of ſaying poſitively <hi>that a Standing Army is inconſiſtent with a Free Government, and abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the Engliſh Monarchy,</hi> he ought to have qualified it thus, <hi>That a Standing Army in time of Peace, unleſs it be by Conſent of Parliament, is Inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with a Free Government, and abſolutely deſtructive to the Engliſh Monarchy,</hi> or which is all one, <hi>againſt Law;</hi> and for this We have the Authority of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention ſign'd with that of Their Majeſties King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY,</hi> who accepted of the Crown upon Agreeing to this and other things relating to the Liberty of the Subject, as is to be ſeen in the Claim of Right.</p>
            <p>But in the Threſhold, I finding my ſelf oblig'd to do the Author ſo much Juſtice as to ſay, that the Writers of the <hi>Reflections</hi> and <hi>Remarks</hi> upon him have ſhew'd a great deal more of Malice and Raſhneſs than of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Argument, when they brand him as a <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobite,</hi> or a <hi>Republican:</hi> In my Opinion the Gentleman
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65765:4"/>hath ſufficiently provided againſt ſuch Imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by pleading all along againſt thoſe things that he thinks deſtructive to the <hi>Engliſh Monarchy:</hi> but it hath been the Conſtant Practice of a Certain Party in the Nation, to blaſt all endeavours for the Liberty of their Countrey, with the Calumny of ſetting up for a Republick, in order to make the beſt Patriots hateful to the Court, and that they might either procure or be continued in places themſelves, or at leaſt to ſerve a Faction that are for Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; which of theſe, or whether all or any of them be the Motives of thoſe Writers that have ſo rudely treated the Author of the Argument, I ſhall not ſo much as preſume to Conjecture, becauſe I am alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unacquainted with their Perſons and Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, as I am indeed with his.</p>
            <p>But to come to the matter, The Caſe is now altered from what it was when either of them wrote, His Majeſty, who is part of the Legiſlative Power, having declar'd His Opinion to the Parliament, that the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of Affairs abroad are ſuch, <hi>That for the preſent,</hi> England <hi>cannot be ſafe without a Land-force.</hi> I his coming from the Mouth of the King, who ſits at the Helm of the Government, and of ſuch a King as hath always demonſtrated a fatherly care of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and an inmitable Courage and Conduct in his Adminiſtration, ſets the matter in quite another Light. Then ſeeing His Majeſty is undoubtedly able to ſatisfy the Nation as to the Truth of his Aſſertion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65765:5"/>The Queſtion is about the neceſſity of a ſtanding Army, how numerous that Army muſt be, of what Troops Compoſed, for how long they muſt be kept up, and what are the moſt proper methods to prevent the dangers which the Argument inſiſts upon, to be the Natural Conſequences of a ſtanding Army, in caſe of His Majeſties Death, and a Succeſſor, who may perhaps be Acted by other Councils, and not endowed with the Royal Qualifications that all Men allow His Majeſty to be bleſſed With. Now that this is neceſſary to be conſidered will be denied by no Man that wiſhes well to our Religion and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, ſeeing it muſt be granted, that His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty is liable to a Violent or Natural Death as well as other Men, and more Obnoxious to the former, becauſe of the Malicious Plots of his exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Enemies.</p>
            <p>What methods are moſt proper to reach thoſe deſirable Ends, muſt be left to the Wiſdom of the King and Parliament to determine, but that there is a danger in keeping a ſtanding Army, as well as in being without one, is ſo obvious that it cannot well be denied, and therefore there is a neceſſity of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king proviſion in both reſpects, which no doubt may be effected without ſuch Heat and Clamour, as the Pamphletears againſt the Arguments are full of, The <hi>Letter for Ballancing excepted,</hi> which is indeed modeſt and to the point.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65765:5"/>
            <p>That we are in danger without a <hi>Standing Army</hi> is reaſonably enough inſiſted on from the Power of the <hi>French</hi> King; his Levity in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving former Treaties, which the Anſwers to the Argument make a mighty noiſe about, and to this may be added, that the Principles of that Religion, whereof the <hi>French</hi> King is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Champion, allows the Breach of the moſt Solemn Ties, and the Perpetration of the moſt horrid Crimes to advance the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. So that all thoſe things conſider'd, there is an abſolute Neceſſity that we ſhould be on our Guard: and as Matters are at preſent, how we can any way be reputed to be ſo without a Standing Force, is to me unconceivable.</p>
            <p>I know that to alleviate thoſe juſt Cauſes of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion it is argued that he is now grown an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient; that his Country is exhauſted of Men, as are his Treaſuries of Money, that his gaining ſo little by breach of former Treaties, hath convinc'd him that 'twill be his Intereſt to obſerve this, and that in ſhort his Country ſtands in need of a time of breathing, ſo that there's nothing now to be fear'd from that Head.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:65765:6"/>
            <p>To this it may be replied, that <hi>Marius Caius,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Conſul, recover'd himſelf, though an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile, ſentenc'd to Death, and abandon'd by all Men, when well ſtricken in Years, and aveng'd himſelf ſufficiently on thoſe that had reduc'd him to thoſe Straits; that though <hi>France</hi> be exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Men, yet the laſt Campaigne is enough to demonſtrate that he's ſtill able to match the Allies for Numbers; and though it muſt be granted that his Treaſures are pretty well emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, yet if it be well conſider'd what an Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Author of that Country did lately write in the Ruin and Deſolation of <hi>France,</hi> demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated his Clergy, who poſſeſs one half of all the Eſtates Real and Perſonal in that Kingdom, are ſtill in a manner untouch'd, though poſſeſs'd of Immenſe Riches; ſo that if he ſhould take the ſame Meaſures with his Popiſh Clergy, as <hi>Guſtavus Erickſon,</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> did with his, or as our <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. did with ours; that is to ſay, turn them out of their Monaſteries, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies and Riches, which is eaſie for him to do with his <hi>Standing Army,</hi> who by the ſacking of Churches and Religious Houſes in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> have given proof enough to the World that they have no Scruple of Conſcience to be ſo imploy'd: I ſay, If he ſhould take this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65765:6"/>Courſe, he would quickly abound with Men and Money, and as eaſily overflow his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Countrys, if they had no <hi>Standing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> to reſiſt him, as the Sea driven by a ſtrong Wind, would overflow <hi>Weſt-Friezland</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> if they ſhould demoliſh their Banks and Dikes.</p>
            <p>Then, as to the Deſolation of his Country, it's rather an Argument that he is to be dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than deſpiſed, conſidering what vaſt Numbers of Diſciplined Troops he has on foot; who to be ſure, if they had their choice, had rather be plundering their rich Neighbours, live in Plenty, and enjoy all the Liberty that's commonly allow'd Soldiers in an Enemy's Country, than be expos'd at home to mannure Deſolate Lands, and cultivate Ruin'd Vineyards, without the Proſpect of any higher Reward than Wooden-Shooes or Canvas-Shirts, and at the ſame time to be liable to all manner of Exorbitant Taxes. And as a Military Life, muſt needs be more Eligible to them after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years being accuſtomed to it, there's no doubt but it would likewiſe be more agreeable to his Aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Genius, if he did not find himſelf in danger of being overmatch'd; and if we conſult the Hiſtories of the <hi>Goths, Vandals, Alans, Huns, &amp;c.</hi> who like an Inundation, did overſpread <hi>Europe</hi> ſucceſſively,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65765:7"/>we ſhall find that their want of a comfortable Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance at home was one of the main Cauſes of thoſe Eruptions they made upon their Neighbours abroad, and there's no Body acquainted with the preſent Condition of <hi>France,</hi> but knows that the Soldiers liv'd much better in the Armies than the Peaſants and ordinary Tradeſmen did at home, and that was one great Reaſon why his Armies were always ſo Numerous.</p>
            <p>As to his being convinc'd by his gaining ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle by the Breach of other Treaties, that 'twill be his Intereſt to obſerve this, I ſhall be very willing to allow that he is poſſeſs'd with ſo Generous and Magnanimous a Soul, that he abhors to do any thing that's baſe; but ſeeing he is ſo unhappy as to be of a Church which pretends to hallow the ungodlieſt Means, ſo they be but effectual to attain their end, they transform Vice in Virtue, and make him to think it his greateſt Glory to perpetrate ſuch things; which without that Biaſs he would think highly diſhonourable. Then as to his Gains by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Breaches, tho it's true he hath had a ſecret Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, which hath made him to diſgorge many Towns and Countries, yet he is ſtill a great Gainer by the Bargain, and retains conſiderable Conqueſts both from <hi>Spain</hi> and the Empire.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:65765:7"/>
            <p>It is alſo further to be obſerved, that tho the <hi>French</hi> King cannot ſo eaſily invade us as he can do his Neighbours on the Continent, yet by this Peace he hath in ſome meaſure diſſolv'd the League, that 'twill not be eaſie to aſſemble again ſo many Troops belonging to ſo many different Princes to oppoſe him, and he hath moreover thrown in a Bone of Contention betwixt the Proteſtant Princes of the Empire, and the Emperour who hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Robbing of the Proteſtants of ſo many of their Churches, which no doubt will highten thoſe miſ-underſtandings, that have been obſervable enough betwixt the Proteſtants and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in <hi>Germany</hi> during the War, and whilſt they are divided amongſt themſelves upon a Religious Account, there's little appearance that either Branch of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> will give any aſſiſtance to us, and for the Proteſtants of <hi>Germany,</hi> they are likely to have work enough to defend themſelves, if any Rupture happen on the Account of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo that we ſeem to be under an abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of putting our ſelves in ſuch a Condition, as we may be able to ſtand on our own bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:65765:8"/>
            <p>There's another thing ſtill, which is of very great Conſequence, tho ſome perhaps may think it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, and that is the fair Proſpect which the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon</hi> has, of having the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> United to that of <hi>Etance</hi> — Their hopes in this matter ſeem not ill founded nor remote, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that weak State of the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Health, their being no likelihood of his having any Iſſue, the ſtrong Faction which the <hi>French</hi> King has in <hi>Spain,</hi> the weakneſs of that Kingdom to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him in caſe of an Invaſion, and then being cut off from all Proſpect of help (if they make any Efforts to preſerve their Liberties) but what they may probably have from us. This Conſideration alone ſhews the neceſſity of our having a Land-Force in readineſs, either to defend. <hi>Flanders,</hi> our Natural Barrier from being ſwallowed up by the <hi>French</hi> King, who will then have a better Title to it than ever, or to be Tranſported to the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in their own Country; for if the Crown of <hi>France</hi> become once poſſeſs'd of <hi>Spain</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> we are, humanely ſpeaking, blockt up on all ſides, our Trade muſt every where be at their Mercy, and we are liable to their Invaſions, without any Proſpect of relief; for as I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd already, they have Created a diverſion for the <hi>German</hi> Proteſtants, the United Provinces are in the very Mouth of the Lion, and the <hi>French</hi> will take care to daſh the <hi>Northern</hi> Crowns one
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65765:8"/>againſt another. All theſe things being conſidered, do in my Opinion demonſtrates an unavoidable danger from the Circumſtances of Affairs abroad, if we be left without a Land Force at home, and therefore tho the Court inſiſt upon it, there's no Reaſon to ſuſpect that they have any Deſign up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Liberties of their own Subjects, when there's ſo much cauſe to provide againſt Forreign Enemies.</p>
            <p>But now on the other Hand, that there is danger from a ſtanding Army at home, is equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrable; as will appear from the following Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Country hath always look'd upon them as a Grievance in time of Peace, could never di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt their Rude behaviour and ſlow pay, and were much diſguſted by their ill Morals.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The renewed attempts of the Court in the Late Reigns, to enſlave the Country by ſtanding Armies, hath made their averſion to them Natural and in a manner Hereditary, ſo that the Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie on that Head is almoſt incurable.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:65765:9"/>
            <p n="3">3. So long as there's a Party in the Kingdom that is not ſufficiently purged of the old Leaven of Paſſive Obedience, and the Army not reform'd in Morals; the preſent Government, which is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Principles diametrically oppoſite to the former, and hath alway, declar'd it ſelf againſt Debauchery, can never be ſafe, if ever the late King or his pretended Son ſhould land with a <hi>French</hi> Power, except the Army be othtrwiſe modell'd than at preſent; for if the debauch'd Soldiers be once poſſeſs'd by theſe Paſſive Obedience-Men, and the Jacobite Gentry in the Country, who have always declar'd a greater good Liking to Popery than to Diſſenters; that the preſent Government is not throughly well affected to the Church, which is the common Topick of the diſaffected Party, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the King's being bred in <hi>Holland,</hi> his grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Liberty of Conſcience in <hi>England,</hi> and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Presbytry in <hi>Scotland;</hi> I ſay, that if once the Army be poyſon'd with thoſe Suggeſtions, that to gether with the continual Exclamations of the Jacobite Party againſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> may very much endanger the preſent government, by the revolt of ſuch a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> in caſe of any ſuch Invaſion as above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65765:9"/>
            <p>So long as a ſtanding Army continues on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent footing, not only the Diſſenters, but all the moderate Church of <hi>England</hi> men, and thoſe called Whiggs in general, will continue uneaſie and be afraid of Invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in caſe of his Majeſty's Death, upon their Liberty and Property, as it happened in the late Reign, ſo that there is cauſe to fear that the Jealouſies of the two Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may throw the Nation into new Convulſions, and the Army, as in all probability it will, joining with the Court, Liberty and Property will be again in danger of being ſwallowed up, the Nation engag'd in a Civil War, and expos'd to a Foreign Conqueſt after the two Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties have weaken'd themſelves by mutual Slaughter and Bloodſhed.</p>
            <p>The Caſe then being thus, and the dangers Great and Eminent in both reſpects, it follows of courſe, that the neareſt ought to be provided againſt firſt, and that is to be done by a Land Force, till ſuch time as the K. and Parliament are ſatisfied that the danger from abroad is over.</p>
            <p>But then, conſidering on the other hand that we have no Leaſe of the Kings Life, proviſion ought to be made againſt the other as ſpeedily as may be; but the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of doing this muſt be choſen and determined by the King and Parliament.</p>
            <p>The Argument propoſes as a defence againſt Foreign Invaſion, the Regulating the Militia, ſo as to make them ſerviceable: The training up of all the Subjects in the uſe of Arms, and keeping a good Fleet, ſo diſpoſed in Convenient Ports as to prevent an Invaſion.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:65765:10"/>
            <p>This in my opinion is highly reaſonable, and were it brought to paſs, would prove a very effectual Remedy both againſt Invaders from abroad and Tyrants at home; but the miſchief on't is, that it is neither done nor like to be done time enough to anſwer the Ends; and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is ſo, no reaſonable Man can think that the Nation ſhould be laid naked without a defence in the mean time; and this I confeſs is the main thing wherein I diſſent from that Ingenious Paper: I am far from the opinion of his Adverſaries, who reproach him as a Republican, Apoſtate Whigg, Jacobite, ſowre Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd, Whimſical and Melancholy Fellow, nor do I think they diſcover much Judgment in ridiculing his propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal as to the Militia and Navy. It is ceretain that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly this Nation did as Remarkable Exploits againſt the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> when they had no ſtanding Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as ever they have done ſince, and that the Battles betwixt the two Houſes of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Barons and the King were fought with as much bravery and order, tho' the Armies conſiſted only of the Country Men and Retainers of either Party, as ever have been done ſince ſtanding Armies came in faſhion. Nor can there be any reaſon aſſigned why the Militia ſhould not equal the Regular Forces, as they are now called, either for Valour or Diſcipline, provided they were equally Train'd as all the people of the Nation were in thoſe times; but the true reaſon why the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia come ſo far ſhort of the Regular Troops now is that the Court having in the late Reigns framed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a diſtinct Intereſt from the Country, they durſt not entruſt them with Arms, nor encourage their being train'd up in the uſe of them; but bleſſed be God the caſe is otherwiſe now, his Majeſty is ſenſible, and hath
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65765:10"/>from time to time expreſs'd his ſenſe of the Affections of his people, and declar'd <hi>That he neither has nor can have any Intereſt diſtinct from theirs.</hi> It was their affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſettled him on the Throne, and hath ever ſince kept him in it, ſo that the better his Subjects are train'd up in martial Diſcipline, the more firmly is his Crown fix'd.</p>
            <p>It is equally certain that there are fewer Mercenary Soldiers and Officers in the Militia; as Originally conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, and more of the Free-holders and Subſtantial Men of the Nation, than in a ſtanding Army, and no man can doubt but the Maſter of a Family, his Son or truſty Servant, will fight with another ſort of Zeal for their own Property and Poſſeſſions, than a Mercenary Soldier, who, as the Argument ſays too true, makes a Profeſſion to be a Butcher of Men for 6 <hi>d.</hi> per. day with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſidering what Cauſe he engages in, and that there are too many ſuch in our Army, cannot be denied by any Perſon that hath not bankrupt all his modeſty; and as for thoſe ſilly inſtances which his Advarſaries inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Militia's not having acted their parts, the reaſon is plain they were not Diſciplin'd, which was the fault of the Government and not of the people; it is moreover a very falſe way of Argumentation to conclude, becauſe the Militia as neglected in the late Reigns, were not to be compared to the Regular Troop can never be brought to be as uſefull in the defence o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Country as a ſtanding Army in other Reigns, but the truth of the matter is, thoſe Authors are not willing to have it put to the Experiment.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:65765:11"/>
            <p>The Argument owns that the Militia is not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for Conpueſts indeed as for Defence, and for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts we have no occaſion to make any, nor were we ever very happy in preſerving them. Yet if all the Males of the Nation were brought up to the uſe of Arms on Holy-days, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which were a more commendable way of ſpending their time than has of late been practiſed. We ſhould not need to fear our King's wanting diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plined Men to go abroad with him on occaſion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out putting the 10000 <hi>l.</hi> Men as one of the Pamphlets calls them to the trouble of doing ſo; nor is it very decent in any perſon to caſt ſuch an unbecomeing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon that Royal Regiment of Citizens, whom his Majeſty honoured to be their Colonel himſelf, but perſons of thoſe Authors kidney had rather belike ſee Arms in the hands of a Dammee, than in the hands of a Sober Citizen: Vice is always afraid of Virtue, but ſpecially when in a Capacity to ſuppreſs it. Some of the Gang remember the blows ſtill they received from the hands of the Citizens, in the late Parliament Wars, and don't care to rencounter with ſuch Adverſaries any more, they had rather contribute to debauch them in Taverns and Play-houſes, as being indeed the readier way to have their Wives and Daughters, nay and their Purſes too at their Devotion.</p>
            <p>The Argument does alſo propoſe a mixing of the Standing Army, or part of 'em at leaſt with the Militia, in order to train them, and to provide for themſelves, which his Adverſaries do mightily ridicule and alledge that all the dangers he fancies from a Standing Army would continue in that caſe, but I muſt beg leave to diſſent from thoſe Gentlemen, they know well enough that the frequent exchange of Gariſons on the Frontiers
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65765:11"/>of Kingdoms is practiſed as an effectual means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent traiterous Corriſpondences in thoſe Gariſons, and that the mixing of numerous Deſerters among other Troops, is lookt on as a good way to prevent any ill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns they may have in deſerting; then why ſhould not the mixing of the Regular Troops amongſt the whole Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia of the Kingdom, where the Soldiers have neither the ſame Officers, Comrades nor the like opportunities to do miſchief were they ſo inclined, as they had when in a ſeparate ſtanding Army: And moreover the Officers of the Militia are or ought all to be Men of Eſtate or Note, and of good Report and Credit where they live, and the Militia Men themſelves not making War their Trade, but being only called out upon an Exigent for the Defence of their Country, they can never be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be ſo rude and deſtructive to the places where they are quartered, as the Souldiers of a Standing Army generally are, many of whoſe Officers, eſpecially ſince buying and ſelling of Commiſſions came in faſhion, are known to be Men of no Eſtate nor Reputation, but preferr'd either for their Money or becauſe perhaps they have been <hi>Valet de Chambres,</hi> or otherwiſe ferviceable to a Superiour Officer, and ſo have neither Honour nor Probity to reſtrain them from ill practiſes themſelves, or to oblige them to puniſh them in others, as Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Note in their reſpective Counties have or ought to have, or otherwiſe are not fit to be intruſted with Command.</p>
            <p>Theſe Gentlemen do likewiſe ridicule the Arguments propoſal of a Good Fleet at Sea, as not ſufficient to prevent an Invaſion, becauſe his preſent Majeſty made his Deſcent notwithſtanding K. <hi>James</hi>'s Fleet; and that the <hi>French</hi> landed Men in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and have gone out
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65765:12"/>and into their own Ports, when our Squadrons have been lying before them, and chiefly becauſe they ſuppoſe that the ſame Wind which brings the <hi>French</hi> from their Coaſts, may keep our fleet Wind-bound upon our own.</p>
            <p>In this part as in all the reſt, they deal very unfair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with our Ingenious Author, he does not propoſe the relying upon a Fleet only, but would have the whole Nation train'd in the Exerciſe of Arms, to oppoſe any Invader: Nor do they at all take notice of his Project, of having ur Fleet ſo diſpoſed into Squadrons, as at the Lands End, <hi>Plimouth,</hi> &amp;c. That it would be impra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable for the <hi>French</hi> to Invade us, let the Wind lie how it will, without expoſing their Tranſport Ships at leaſt to one or other of thoſe Squadrons. As to their Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the King's making his Deſcent notwithſtanding King <hi>James</hi>'s Fleet, it is nothing to the purpoſe, had the ſaid Fleet been ſo diſpos'd as our Author propoſes the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet could not ſo eaſily have eſcaped them; but we are moreover to believe that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had his Friends in the Fleet as well as in the Army, which does perfectly alter the Caſe.</p>
            <p>Then as to the <hi>French</hi> having landed Men in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and gone out and into their own Ports, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Squadrons lying before them, the Authors know that in moſt or all of thoſe Caſes, there have been ſhrewd ſuſpicions of Treachery, or a real or pretended want of Orders, Proviſions, or ſomewhat: Nay, as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the eſcape of the <hi>Thoulon</hi> Fleet through the Straits once, and their getting into <hi>Brest</hi> at another time, have been queſtioned in Parliament, and there paſt a Vote in the Houſe, that there was a notorious Treach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery in ſome of our Miſcarriages of that nature, ſo that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65765:12"/>the Anſwerers of the Argument can conclude nothing from this, for that Author always ſuppoſes our Fleet to be honeſt; and the King's Ships to be Commanded either by Gentlemen of known Integrity, or ſuch true Tarrs as the Captain called <hi>Honour and Glory,</hi> and not by Lap dogs as one of our Lampoons repreſented them after <hi>Torrington</hi>'s Defeat, who have ſpent more of their time in the School of <hi>Venus,</hi> than in that of <hi>Mars.</hi> Then as to the equal danger that thoſe Authors ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt from a ſtanding Fleet as from a ſtanding Army, it is very eaſie to ſhew them their miſtake. In the firſt place, they can give us no inſtance of it, that ever our Fleet pillaged or plundred their own Country, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſome few Ships may have done either under <hi>Charles</hi> II. when Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> or at other times, whereas it is very well known that the Army under <hi>Charles</hi> the I, treated the Subjects in as barbarous a manner as a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Enemy would almoſt have done— and the Country does ſtill remeber what horrid diſorders were committed by thoſe of <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>James</hi> II. In the next place, it is plain that if the Fleet ſhould revolt againſt the nation, they forfeit all thoſe pledges they have on ſhoar which are much more conſiderable in proportion than the thoſe of the Land Army, for though we ſhould grant that many of the Land Officers have Eſtates and Families, yet few of the Soldiers have, whereas the far greater part of the Marine Officers have Eſtates and Families and but few of the Seamen are without the latter; and to give them their due, they ſeem to have a better ſenſe of the true Intereſt of the Nation than the Land Soldiers general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have, and hence it came to paſs that the Wappeners were ſo much expos'd to Reflections in the late Reign, and that they have appear'd ſo Zealous for this, and from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65765:13"/>the ſame Cauſe it muſt needs proceed, that not one Ship of the Navy Revolted from the preſent Government tho' <hi>Dumbarton</hi>'s and other Regiments of the ſtanding Army did. But to give thoſe Gentlemen all the ſcope they can deſire, we will ſuppoſe what no man in his right Wits will ever ſuppoſe to be practicable, that the whole Navy ſhould Revolt, and bring in a <hi>French</hi> Army up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us; that could not hinder the Nation from calling in the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Dutch, Daniſh,</hi> and <hi>Swediſh</hi> Men of War to oppoſe them, which their own Intereſt would ſoon prompt them to do, nor yet prevent the people's Arming like one Man to make head againſt the Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Invader, whereas if a ſtanding Army ſhould by the Authority of any ſucceeding Prince join with him to ſwallow up the Liberties of the people, they can effect it ſpeedily, as being in the midſt of us, where they have opportunity to cut off the whole Parliament at a blow, as <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> of <hi>Denmark</hi> did that of <hi>Sweden,</hi> or to Lop of the oppoſite Nobility and Gentry by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and ſo the people having none to Conduct them muſt ſubmit like Sheep without a Shepherd, and I wonder at thoſe Gentlemen who think this impracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, when <hi>Charles</hi> I. came into the Parliament Houſe with an Armed Force and demanded the five Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and <hi>Oliver</hi> by Military Force modelled the Houſe as he himſelf pleas'd, ſo that in either of thoſe Caſes the King and the Uſurper had not God reſtrain'd them, might have done the ſame thing as <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> did —</p>
            <p>There's another pleaſant Fancy which one of thoſe Authors has broached, <hi>viz.</hi> That there's no ſlavery to be fear'd but in Conjunction with Popery, when the whole Nation remembers to this day how near we were
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65765:13"/>enſlaved by <hi>Charles</hi> II. and many of them do ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that had it not been for the <hi>Scotch, Charles</hi> I. had ſwallowed up their Libertys after the defeat of the Parliaments Forces in the Weſt, if not before ever the Parliament ſtruck one ſtroke; and yet Father and Son and <hi>Oliver</hi> the Uſurper too, were all three Proteſtants. And for thoſe Gentlemen's further Conviction, let them look abroad into <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweden,</hi> and tell us whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe Nations did not loſe their Liberty under Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Princes.</p>
            <p>I ſhall agree with thoſe Authors, that his preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty is uncapable of any ſuch thing, that the whole Tenour of his Life, both before and ſince his coming to the Crown, ſecures us againſt any ſuch fears from himſelf; it is evident to the world that inſtead of his ſeeking after a Crown, there were three Crowns that ſought after him, elſe we had never been troubled with ſuch long and learned debates, whither there was an Abdication and Vacaney of the Throne or not. I ſhall moreover be as willing as any of them to ſuppoſe that none of thoſe nam'd in the Succeſſion as now limited will attempt any ſuch thing: But we muſt grant what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays to be true, <hi>That none knowns who ſhall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him, whether a Wiſe Man or a Fool.</hi> We cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways promiſe our ſelves a Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> or ſuch an one as our late Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> nor yet, that every young Prince will prove an <hi>Edward</hi> VI. or that every Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prince that may happen to be match'd with our Heireſſes, ſhall have ſo near a Relation to the Crown as the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> or have ſo much Zeal, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Power as he to reſcue us out of the Jaws of Oppreſſors; and therefore ſeeing it is the practice of all Wiſe Men to provide in a Calm againſt a Storm;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65765:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:65765:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:65765:15"/>I ſee no reaſon why the Author of the Argument ſhould be treated as one diſaffected to his Majeſty's Perſon or Government. Charity, which is almoſt loſt in this Age, would rather think that he has the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Opinion of his Majeſty that can be, when he takes it for granted that he will agree to ſuch Methods in his own Reign, as will ſecure us from Tyranny in thoſe of others, which any Man with half an Eye may ſee to be unavoidable, if the Maxim of the Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be true, <hi>viz. No Army, no King,</hi> when all the World knows there have been and may be, great Kings with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtanding Armies.</p>
            <p>I have exceeded the bounds that I intended at firſt, and ſhall now haſten to a Concluſion. It has been ſaid already that it would ſeem now no more to be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, a ſtanding Army or no ſtanding Army, but how great an Army, of what Troops Compos'd, how long they muſt continue, and what Methods are proper to prevent thoſe ill Conſequences that the Argument ſuggeſts. It's certain the Parliament is the fitteſt Judges of all thoſe things, yet ſeeing every one of the Anſwerers has propoſed his own Methods, its hop'd they will not be angry if I tell them what I have heard propoſed by others,</p>
            <p>It has been a long time the opinion of ſome Men, that had his Majeſty been adviſed to have kept that Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teer Army on foot, which roſe for him on their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, we had prevented the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Sctoland,</hi> and brought <hi>France</hi> to reaſon much ſooner; but ſome Men out of a pretended Zeal to the Church, prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have the contrary method taken, to the no ſmall danger of the State. But if reaſon may take place, now that the Church is ſecured as much as Law can ſecure
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65765:15"/>her, and that ſhe has a Teſt to aſſure her Diſcipline, or rather Government.</p>
            <p>I ſay ſeeing ſhe has a Teſt to ſecure her Government, its but reaſonable the people ſhould have a Teſt too, to preſerve their Property: And their's a Friend of mine ſays that were he to have a Teſt of his making, it ſhould be ſome ſuch one as this, <hi>viz. That, whereas all men in the late Reigns, that came into places of Power and Truſt, were obliged to abhore that Traterous poſition of taking up Arms by the Kings Authority againſt his Perſon, and that they declared there was no obligation upon themſelves or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by that Treaſoinable Oath, called the League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> So now none ſhould be admitted into any place of Power and Truſt, without declaring their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of the Tyranny of the late Reigns, complain'd of in the Claim of Right, and that they account themſelves and others under no obligation to believe the Tyrannical Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience and Non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, as explained and underſtood in the late Reign: But I know my Friend is hot Headed, and that this Pill is not well enough guilded to go down: Yet there are others who are more moderate, that are of opinion, if the Government think fit to allow of a ſtanding Army, the Country would be the more ſatisfied if all or moſt of the Officers be Men of Eſtates and Intereſt in the Nation, and known to be ſuch as think they may go to Heaven without believing the Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience, in the ſenſe above mentioned; and that the ſaid Army be compoſed as much as may be of thoſe that have been raiſed, or are now well mixed by ſuch Gentlemen as always oppoſed the Tyranny of the late Reigns, and that at the ſame time the Militia and Fleet be alſo put into ſuch hands, and the former diſciplin'd
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65765:16"/>with as much ſpeed as may be, now that we have plenty of experienced Officers and Soldiers to do it.</p>
            <p>My Friends are alſo of opinion, that it is our Intereſt to Cultivate a Good Correſpondence with <hi>Scotland,</hi> in order to which an Union of the Nations would be much more effectual than the Union of the Crowns; for that leaves room for Princes of Arbitrary Tempers to daſh us one againſt another, and to make us the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Tyranny by turns. Thus King <hi>Charles</hi> the I. threatned to Invade <hi>Scotland,</hi> and actually did it with an Army from <hi>England;</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the II. procured an Act of Parliament in <hi>Scotland</hi> for 20000 Horſe and Foot, with ſo many days Proviſions, to march to any part of his Dominions that he pleaſed, which conſidering the party in this Nation that would have joyned them, might have been fatal to all the three Kingdoms, had not that Prince been more given to his pleaſures than to his Sword. Such an Union, as no doubt it might be effected, to the Honour and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of both Nations, would alſo ſecure this Nation ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much in caſe of any future War with <hi>France,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; whereas if the <hi>Scotch</hi> be alays treated with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, or govern'd by the Councils of a Party, this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that hates them, on the account of their Civil and Religious Principles, it may have ill Conſequences at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or other. The Royal Line which Cements them at preſent, is not very numerous in Off-ſpring, and that failing, they have Princes of their own Blood at home, who if they ſtrengthen themſelves by powerful foreign Alliances may prove troubleſome Neighbours, when we are engaged in a foreign War, eſpecially conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great plantation of their Countrymen of the ſame Principles with themſelves in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:65765:16"/>
            <p>Which Kingdom my Friends are alſo of opinion ought to be treated ſo as they may look upon themſelves as fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Subjects, and that ſome ſtronger efforts ſhould be made, and more Chriſtian methods taken to Civilize and Convert the Popiſh Natives than have hitherto been practiſed, and then we ſhall be in no danger of having our Brethrens Throats cut by them in their Country, nor of being Invaded by them in our own, as in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> I. and <hi>James</hi> II. If <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> were both united to this Kingdom, upon terms Honourable and Advantagious to us and them, we might ſit as Queen in the Seas, retain our Soveraignty undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, keep the Ballance of <hi>Europe,</hi> nay, of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe in our hands, be ſecure againſt Tyranny at home, and Invaſion from abroad, and <hi>England</hi> would be the unenvi'd Head of the Union. I have alſo heard ſome Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen give their opinion that 'twere the Intereſt of this Nation, to have methods laid down for entertaining a perpetual Amity with <hi>Holland,</hi> leſt future Princes may daſh us againſt one another as formerly, to the endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Civil Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Europe.</hi> The only thing that we can have any occaſion to quarrel about, is our rivalling one another in point of Trade, and as Providence did formerly put an opportunity into the hands of this Nation, of taking away the Hereditary Enmity that had been for ſome Centuries betwixt us and <hi>Scotland,</hi> by uniting the Crowns, kind Heaven hath now alſo put an opportunity into our hands of fixing a perpetual Friendſhip with <hi>Holland,</hi> our King and their Stadholder being one and the ſame perſon, and equally the darling of both People; ſo that there's no reaſon to doubt, but in ſuch an auſpicious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture, matters may be ſo concerted by the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65765:17"/>of both Nations, as to prevent any ſuch competition in time to come, as may occaſion a Rupture. There's cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly room enough in the World for both of us to Trade, and if we entertain a good Correſpondence, we may in a manner divide the Trade of the Univerſe betwixt us; but if by the implacable malice of a certain Faction in this Kingdom againſt that Induſtrious and brave Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, becauſe of their Government being founded upon Principles contrary to Paſſive Obedience, we be kept off from ſetling a parpetual Friendſhip with them, it will certainly argue our infatuation, for there's no Allies we can have that are in any capacity to aſſiſt us againſt <hi>France,</hi> in caſe that already over-grown Monarchy ſhould be yet further aggrandiz'd by addition of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of <hi>Spain,</hi> of which as I have ſaid already, they have ſo fair and near a Proſpect.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the haſty thoughts, Sir, of our Friends here in Town, as to the Arguments <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> about a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Army, which are all at preſent the Common Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Converſation. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:65765:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
